翻译   jurohd
校对   䶭  ZSC  ksyx  鹤翔万里
时轴   鹤翔万里  䶭        后期   鹤翔万里
This is a Galton Board.
这是一个高尔顿钉板
Maybe you've seen one before.
也许你以前见过
It's a popular demonstration
它通常用来说明
of how even when a single event is chaotic and random,
即使某一单独的事件的结果混乱、随机
with an effectively unknowable outcome,
it's still possible to make precise statements about a large number of events,
大量这种事件不同结果的相对比例
namely how the relative proportions for many different outcomes are distributed.
仍能够被准确描述
More specifically, the Galton board illustrates
更具体地说  高尔顿板展示了
one of the most prominent distributions in all of probability,
概率学中一种重要的分布
known as the Normal distribution, more colloquially known as a Bell curve,
“正态分布” 俗称 “钟形曲线”
and also called a Gaussian distribution.
也叫做  “高斯分布”
There's a very specific function to describe this distribution.
有一个非常明确的函数来描述这个分布
Very pretty. We'll get into it later.
我们稍后会深入讨论这个美妙的式子
But right now, I just want to emphasize
但现在我想强调的是
how the normal distribution is, as the name suggests, very common.
为何“正态分布”正是一种常态
It shows up in a lot of seemingly unrelated contexts.
出现在许多看似无关的场景中
If you were to take a large number of people who sit in a similar demographic
假如你调查特征相似的一大批人
and plot their heights, those heights tend to follow a normal distribution.
画出他们的身高分布图  你会发现这往往遵循正态分布
If you look at a large swath of very big natural numbers and you ask
如果随机抽取一堆非常大的自然数
how many distinct prime factors does each one of those numbers have,
记录下它们分别都有多少个不同的质因数
the answers will very closely track with a certain normal distribution.
你会发现答案非常接近于正态分布
Now, our topic for today
我们今天的主题
is one of the crown jewels in all of probability theory.
是概率论的璀璨明珠
It's one of the key facts that explains why this distribution is as common as it is,
也是正态分布之所以如此普遍的一大原因
known as the Central Limit Theorem.
它就是中心极限定理
This lesson is meant to go back to the basics,
这节课的目的是回归基础
giving you the fundamentals on what the Central Limit Theorem is saying,
用最少的背景知识
what normal distributions are, and I want to assume minimal background.
介绍中心极限定理以及正态分布的基本内容
We're going to go decently deep into it, but after this,
我们会讲得挺深  但在此之后
I'd still like to go deeper and explain why the theorem is true,
我仍然想更进一步解释中心极限定理为何成立
why the function underlying the normal distribution
为什么描述正态分布的函数
has the very specific form that it does,
要长成这样子
why that formula has a π in it,
为什么式子里还有个 π
and, most fun, why those last two facts are actually more related
而最有趣的是  正态分布的函数与π之间的联系
than a lot of traditional explanations would suggest.
比很多传统的解释  要来得更紧密
That second lesson is also meant to be
而这一部分
the follow on to the convolutions video that I promised.
也是我之前承诺的卷积视频的后续
So, there's a lot of interrelated topics here.
这里的许多内容都相互关联
But right now, back to the fundamentals.
但让我们先回到基础内容
I'd like to kick things off with an overly simplified model of the Galton board.
从这个过度简化的高尔顿板模型开始
In this model, we will assume that
我们假设
each ball falls directly onto a certain central peg
这个模型中的球会直接掉在钉子中间
and then it has a 50 - 50 probability of bouncing to the left or to the right,
然后以相等的概率向左或向右弹
and we'll think of each of those outcomes
这样一来  这个弹跳的过程
as either adding one or subtracting one from its position.
也就可以理解为  从当前位置向右加一或向左减一
Once one of those is chosen, we make the highly unrealistic assumption that
选择了方向之后  我们还要做一个非常不切实际的假设
it happens to land dead on in the middle of the peg adjacent below it,
那就是它会恰好落在下一层某个钉子的正中间
where again, it'll be faced with the same 50 - 50 choice
然后再次面临向左或向右弹跳的选择
of bouncing to the left or to the right.
For the one I'm showing on screen, there are five different rows of pegs.
对于画面上这个钉板来说  它有五排不同的钉子
So our little hopping ball
所以我们的小球
makes five different random choices between +1 and -1,
要在 +1 和 -1 之间随机选择 5 次
and we can think of its final position
而它的最终位置
as basically being the sum of all of those different numbers.
则可以认为是这些加一减一的总和
Which in this case happens to be one,
画面上这种情况的位置则是 1
and we might label all of the different buckets
而我们则可以用这些总和
with the sum that they represent.
来标记小球最终落入的各个桶
As we repeat this,
我们的重复试验
we're looking at different possible sums for those five random numbers.
则是这五个随机数的和  取到各个值的概率
And for those of you who are inclined to complain
或许有人想抱怨
that this is a highly unrealistic model for the true Galton board
这个模型跟真正的高尔顿板相比太假了
let me emphasize - the goal right now is not to accurately model physics,
我想说的是  现在我们想做的不是去准确模拟物理现象
the goal is to give a simple example to illustrate the central limit theorem,
而是找一个简单的例子来说明中心极限定理
and for that, idealized though this might be,
所以就算它十分理想化
it actually gives us a really good example.
这仍然是一个很不错的例子
If we let many different balls fall,
如果掉下来的不止一个球
making yet another unrealistic assumption that
我们就要再做一个不现实的假设
they don't influence each other, as if they're all ghosts,
假设它们都是幽灵球  互不影响
then the number of balls that fall into each different bucket
那么掉进不同桶里的球的数量
gives us some loose sense for how likely each one of those buckets is.
会大致说明球有多大概率落到每个桶
In this example the numbers are simple enough
这个例子中的数都不复杂
that it's not too hard to explicitly calculate
所以我们可以轻松计算出球落入各个桶的概率
what the probability is for falling into each bucket.
If you do want to think that through,
但是如果你想得足够深
you'll find it very reminiscent of Pascal's triangle,
会发现它让人联想到杨辉三角
but the neat thing about our theorem is
但我们定理的妙处在于
how far it goes beyond the simple examples.
它远远不局限于这样简单的例子
So, to start off at least, rather than making explicit calculations,
所以  一上来我们先不去仔细算
let's just simulating things by running a large number of samples
而是大量重复地模拟这个过程
and letting the total number of results in each different outcome
让这个模拟中每个结果出现的次数
give us some sense for what that distribution looks like.
为我们展示这个分布的大致形状
As I said, the one on screen has five rows,
就像我之前说的  这个屏幕上有五行钉子
so each sum that we're considering includes only five numbers.
也就意味着我们考虑的和只由五个数得出
The basic idea of the central limit theorem
中心极限定理的基本思想是
is that if you increase the size of that sum,
如果你求更多的数的和
for example, here that would mean
例如在这个例子里增加钉子的行数
increasing the number of rows of pegs for each ball to bounce off
让球反弹更多次
then the distribution that describes where that sum is going to fall
就能使各个总和的概率分布
looks more and more like a bell curve.
越来越接近一个钟形曲线
Here, it's actually worth taking a moment to write down that general idea.
我们还是花点时间来写下大致的想法：
The setup is that we have a random variable
首先我们有一个随机变量
and that's basically shorthand for a random process
其实就是把一个随机的过程中
where each outcome of that process is associated with some number.
得到的每个结果都写成一个数
We'll call that random number X.
我们将这个随机变量称为 X
For example, each bounce off the peg
例如每次小球的弹跳
is a random process modeled with two outcomes.
都是一个随机的过程  只有两种结果
Those outcomes are associated with the numbers -1 and +1.
左和右分别记为 -1 和 +1
Another example of a random variable would be rolling a die,
另一个随机变量的例子是掷骰子
where you have six different outcomes each one associated with a number.
总共有六种结果  分别写成 1~6
What we're doing is taking multiple different samples of that variable
而我们要做的就是对这个随机变量多次取样
and adding them all together.
最后全部相加
On our Galton board, that looks like
用高尔顿板的例子来说就是
letting the ball bounce off multiple different pegs
让球在一路下落到底的过程中多次被钉子反弹
on its way down to the bottom,
and in the case of a die, you might imagine
而在骰子的例子中
rolling many different dice and adding up the results.
则是掷很多不同的骰子并将点数相加
The claim of the central limit theorem
中心极限定理说明了
is that as you let the size of that sum get bigger and bigger,
随着相加的随机变量越来越多
then the distribution of that sum,
这个总和的分布
how likely it is to fall into different possible values,
也就是取各种值的概率
will look more and more like a bell curve.
将越来越接近一个钟形曲线
That's it, that is the general idea.
而这也是中心极限定理的大致思想
Over the course of this lesson,
我们这节课的目标
our job is to make that statement more quantitative.
是去量化这个笼统的描述
We're going to put some numbers to it,
为这个描述添上一些数和式子
put some formulas to it,
show how you can use it to make predictions.
并展示如何用它进行预测
For example, here's the kind of question
例如 看完这个视频以后
I want you to be able to answer by the end of this video:
我希望你能回答像下面这种问题
suppose you roll the die 100 times, and you added together the results.
假设你准备掷 100 次骰子  并把点数加起来
Could you find a range of values
请报出一个取值范围
such that you're 95% sure that the sum will fall within that range.
能够保证有 95% 的把握 总和会落在这个范围内
Or maybe I should say,
我还应该加上一句
find the smallest possible range of values such that this is true.
这个要寻找的范围越窄越好
The neat thing is, you'll be able to answer this question
神奇的是  无论你掷的骰子是否均匀
whether it's a fair die or if it's a weighted die.
你总能回答这个问题
Now, let me say at the top
让我把话放在前面
that this theorem has three different assumptions that go into it.
中心极限定理有三条假设
Three things that have to be true before the theorem follows
它们是定理成立的前提条件
and I'm actually not going to tell you what they are until the very end of the video.
不过具体要等到视频的结尾我才会告诉你
Instead, I want you to keep your eye out
但我希望你看仔细点
and see if you can notice and maybe predict
看看是否能注意到并猜出
what those three assumptions are going to be.
这三个假设究竟是什么
As a next step to better illustrate just how general this theorem is,
为了更好地说明这个定理有多通用
I want to run a couple more simulations for you focused on the dice example.
我想先多模拟几个掷骰子的例子
Usually, if you think of rolling a die,
通常  如果你掷一个骰子
you think of the six outcomes as being equally probable,
你会认为六个结果是等概率的
but the theorem actually doesn't care about that.
但是定理并不在意这个条件
We could start with a weighted die
我们可以从一个偏心骰子开始
something with a non-trivial distribution across the outcomes
它的结果分布并不均匀
and the core idea still holds,
但定理的核心观点却仍然成立
for the simulation what will do is take some distribution,
我们可以取一个分布来进行模拟
like this one that is skewed towards lower values.
例如这个更容易丢出小点数的骰子
I'm going to take 10 distinct samples from that distribution,
然后我从这个分布中抽十个样本
and then I'll record the sum of that sample on the plot, on the bottom.
在下面的频率图上记录这些样本的和
Then I'm going to do this many many different times.
反复进行这个过程
Always with the sum of size 10
每次抽十个样本
but keep track of where those sums ended up
把和标记在频率图上
to give us a sense of the distribution.
让我们对这个和的分布有个直观理解
And in fact, let me rescale the y direction
事实上 我可以把这个图压扁一点
to give us room to run an even larger number of samples,
给后面模拟的结果预留空间
and I'll let it go all the way up to a couple thousand
然后跑个几千轮模拟
and as it does, you'll notice that the shape that starts to emerge
在这个过程中  你会注意到这个分布的形状开始变化
looks like a bell curve.
变得越来越像一个钟形曲线
Maybe if you squint your eyes you can see it skews a tiny bit to the left,
虽然可能你眯起眼睛会发现它有点往左偏
but it's neat that something so symmetric
可神奇的是如此对称的图像
emerged from a starting point that was so asymmetric.
居然是用偏心骰子的分布模拟出来的
To better illustrate what the central limit theorem is all about,
为了更好地解释中心极限定理到底是什么
let me run four of these simulations in parallel.
让我同时模拟这四个东西
Where on the upper left I'm doing it - we're only adding two dice at a time.
左上角是两个偏心骰子的点数和
On the upper right, we're doing it where we're adding five dice at a time,
右上角是一次五个骰子的点数和
the lower left is the one that we just saw, adding 10 dice at a time
左下角是我们刚刚模拟的十个骰子的点数和
and then we'll do another one with a bigger sum, 15 at a time.
最后右下角我们搞个大的  模拟 15 个骰子的点数和
Notice how on the upper left when we're just adding two dice,
注意到在左上角我们只有两个骰子的时候
the resulting distribution doesn't really look like a bell curve,
点数和的分布看起来并不像钟形曲线
it looks a lot more reminiscent of the one we started with -
它更像偏心骰子本身
skewed towards the left.
更容易掷出小点数的那个分布
But as we allow for more and more dice in each sum,
但是随着我们用的骰子越来越多
the resulting shape that comes up in these distributions
得到的这个点数和分布的形状
looks more and more symmetric.
就会越来越对称
It has the lump in the middle and fade towards the tail shape of a bell curve.
它的形状中间凸起两端逐渐平缓  趋近钟形曲线
Let me emphasize again, you can start with any different distribution.
要强调的是  这个规律用任意点数分布的骰子都适用
Here I'll run it again
然后我再模拟一次
but where most of the probability is tied up in the numbers 1 and 6
但这次骰子十分可能掷出 1 和 6
with very low probability for the mid values.
几乎不可能掷出中间点数
Despite completely changing the distribution for an individual roll of the die,
尽管完全改变了骰子点数的概率分布
it's still the case that a bell curve shape will emerge
当我们记录这些不同总和数值出现的次数时
as we consider the different sums.
我们仍然观察到钟形曲线形状逐渐形成
Illustrating things with a simulation like this is very fun
用这样的模拟来解释这个定理非常有趣
and it's kind of neat to see order emerge from chaos
并且神奇的是  无论一开始多么混乱  最终都归于钟形曲线
but it also feels a little imprecise. Like in this case.
但它也如现在展示的这样  没有那么精确
When I cut off the simulation at 3000 samples,
当我只运行三千次模拟的时候
even though it kind of looks like a bell curve,
尽管能观察到钟形曲线的样子
the different buckets seem pretty spiky?
但是中间还是有几个峰
And you might wonder is it supposed to look that way
你可能会想  它究竟是一个必然结果
or is that just an artifact of the randomness in the simulation,
还是只是众多模拟中的偶然
and if it is, how many samples do we need
如果是的话  那我们到底需要多少样本
before we can be sure that what we're looking at
才能确信我们现在看到的图像
is representative of the true distribution?
能够代表真实分布情况呢
Instead moving forward, let's get a little more theoretical
在更深入探讨之前  先来了解一些理论知识
and show the precise shape that these distributions will take on in the long run.
使得我们能精确描述总和分布随着更多骰子加入的变化
The easiest case to make this calculation is if we have a uniform distribution,
最简单的情况是我们有一个公平的骰子
where each possible face of the die has an equal probability, 1/6.
它掷出骰子的每一面点数的概率都是 1/6
For example, if you then want to know
例如  如果你想知道
how likely different sums are for a pair of dice,
掷一对骰子之后有多大概率点数和是某个数
it's essentially a counting game,
这就变成了一个计数游戏
where you count up
因为你可以确切数出
how many distinct pairs take on the same sum.
有多少对投掷结果  有着相同的点数和
Which in the diagram I've drawn,
在我画的示意图中
you can conveniently think about by going through all of the different diagonals.
各个斜线上的点数和都相同
Since each such pair has an equal chance of showing up, 1 in 36,
并且掷出各对骰子的概率都是 1/36
all you have to do is count the sizes of these buckets.
你只要数有多少种组合可以得到某个点数和
That gives us a definitive shape for the distribution describing a sum of two dice
就能够得到准确的点数和概率分布
and if we were to play the same game with all possible triplets,
如果我们把骰子增加到三个
the resulting distribution would look like this.
那么我们得到的分布长这样
Now, what's more challenging but a lot more interesting is to ask
现在更有挑战也更有趣的问题是
what happens if we have a non-uniform distribution for that single die.
换成偏心骰子以后会发生什么
We actually talked all about this in the last video.
其实我们在上一个视频中已经讨论过这个问题
You do essentially the same thing, you go through all the distinct
你只需要做和刚刚相同的事情
pairs of dice which add up to the same value.
找出相同点数和的不同骰子组合
It's just that instead of counting those pairs,
只是你不能光数个数
for each pair, you multiply the two probabilities of each particular face coming up
而是要把每对里两个点数的概率相乘
and then you add all those together.
然后把所有点数和相同的概率加在一起
The computation that does this for all possible sums has a fancy name,
这个计算各个点数和概率的过程  其实有个高大上的名字
it's called a Convolution
叫 卷积
but it's essentially just the weighted version of the counting game
但本质上它只是带权重的计数游戏
that anyone who's played with a pair of dice already finds familiar.
刚刚认真听课的同学肯定不会陌生
For our purposes, in this lesson, I'll have the computer calculate all that,
为了减少不必要的麻烦  这些运算全部由计算机进行
simply display the results for you and invite you to observe certain patterns,
然后把结果展示给你  指引你发现其中的规律
but under the hood, this is what's going on.
而刚刚所介绍的这些  则是幕后的运算过程
So, just to be crystal clear on what's being represented here,
为了让你完全理解这都在干啥
if you imagine sampling two different values from that top distribution,
假设从最上面的那个单个骰子点数概率的分布图中
the one describing a single die and adding them together,
取两个点数加在一起
then the second distribution I'm drawing
那么我下面画的那个分布
represents how likely you are to see various different sums.
表示相加得到各个点数和的概率
Likewise, if you imagine
同理  假设从最上面的分布中取三个不同的值
sampling three distinct values from that top distribution
然后把它们加在一起
and adding them together,
在这种情况下各个点数和的概率
the next plot represents the probabilities for various different sums in that case.
则是像最下面这张图展现的一样
So, if I compute what the distributions for these sums look like
依此类推  如果我像这样计算不同点数和的概率分布
for larger and larger sums,
当我用的骰子数越来越多时
well, you know what I'm going to say, it looks more and more like a bell curve.
我猜你已经知道我要说什么了  它会长得越来越像钟形曲线
But before we get to that, I want you to make a couple more simple observations.
但在我们讨论这个现象之前  我希望你再简单观察一些规律
For example, these distributions seem to be wandering to the right,
例如  这些分布的图像在不断向右偏移
and also they seem to be getting more spread out and a little bit more flat.
而且分布得越来越宽  图像也慢慢变扁平
You cannot describe the central limit theorem quantitatively
如果不考虑上面这两种现象
without taking into account both of those effects,
你将很难定量描述中心极限定理
which in turn requires describing the mean and the standard deviation.
而这就要求我们能够描述它们的均值和标准差
Maybe you're already familiar with those,
或许你已经对这两个概念很熟悉了
but I want to make minimal assumptions here and it never hurts to review.
不过我不会假设看这个视频的都了解  而且复习一下也无妨
So let's quickly go over both of those.
那么让我们快速回顾一下这两个概念
The mean of a distribution, often denoted with a Greek letter μ,
一个分布的均值  通常用希腊字母 μ 表示
is a way of capturing the center of mass for that distribution.
描述了这个分布的重心
It's calculated as the expected value of our random variable,
而它的值恰好是随机变量的期望值
which is a way of saying you go through all of the different possible outcomes
在这里  期望意味着
and you multiply the probability of that outcome times the value of the variable.
把这个随机变量各个取值乘以对应的概率的结果加起来
If higher values are more probable, that weighted sum is going to be bigger,
这样一来  如果更可能出现较大的值  这个加权和会更大
if lower values are more probable, that weighted time is going to be smaller.
反之  如果更可能出现较小的数值  这个加权和也会更小
A little more interesting is if you want to measure
而测量这个分布的范围有多广
how spread out this distribution is,
由于许多不同的概念都可以做到
because there's multiple different ways you might do it.
就显得更有意思了
One of them is called the variance.
其中一种方法叫做方差
The idea there is to look at the difference
它是通过先计算
between each possible value and the mean,
随机变量各个取值与均值之间的差
square that difference and ask for its expected value.
并取这个差值的平方作为新的随机变量求期望
The idea is that whether your value is below or above the mean,
这样一来  无论你的随机变量取值是低于还是高于均值
when you square that difference you get a positive number
当你取这个差值的平方时  你总能得到一个正数
and the larger the difference, the bigger that number.
而且差值越大  这个数值也越大
Squaring it like this turns out to make the math
并且取平方的过程使得这个运算
much, much nicer than if we did something like an absolute value,
比诸如绝对值的其他方法要好得多
but the downside is that it's hard to think about this as a distance
但缺点是  我们不好把它当作图中的距离
in our diagram because the units are off.
因为单位不匹配
Kind of like the units here are square units
这里的单位更像是平方单位
whereas a distance in our diagram would be a kind of linear unit.
而图中我们想描述的这个差值应该是线性单位的
So, another way to measure spread is what's called the standard deviation,
因此  另一种测量分布范围宽度的方法就是用标准差
which is the square root of this value.
其实就是方差的平方根
That can be interpreted much more reasonably as a distance on our diagram
这样一来  我们可以更合理地把它说成是在图上的“距离”
and it's commonly denoted with the Greek letter σ.
通常用希腊字母 σ 表示
So, you know m for mean, as for standard deviation but both in Greek.
也就是  m 表示均值  s 表示标准差  只不过用希腊字母表示
Looking back at our sequence of distributions,
回顾一下刚刚图中的一系列分布
let's talk about the mean and standard deviation.
我们可以谈谈均值和标准差
If we call the mean of the initial distribution μ,
如果我们把最早提到的数值分布的均值称为 μ
which for the one Illustrated happens to be 2.24,
对于图上所示的这个例子 μ 恰好是 2.24
hopefully, it won't be too surprising
而要是我告诉你下一个的分布均值是 2μ
if I tell you that the mean of the next one is two times μ.
你应该不会被惊到吧
That is, you roll a pair of dice, you want to know the expected value of the sum,
换句话说  当你求一对骰子点数和的期望时
it's two times the expected value for a single die.
它是单个骰子点数期望值的两倍
Similarly, the expected value for our sum of size 3 is 3 times mu
而类似的  三个骰子点数和的期望是 3μ
and so on and so forth. The mean just marches steadily on to the right,
依此类推  每加一个骰子  均值就会向右移动一些
which is why our distributions seem to be drifting off in that direction.
这就是为什么我们发现分布整体在朝右移动
A little more challenging but very important
而更有挑战但非常重要的一点是
is to describe how the standard deviation changes.
描述标准差是怎么变化的
The key fact here is that if you have two different random variables,
关键点在于  如果你有两个随机变量
then the variance for the sum of those variables
那么这两个变量之和的方差
is the same as just adding together the original two variances.
和将原始的两个变量方差相加所得到的值完全相同
This is one of those facts that you can just compute
在用上了一堆的定义以后
when you unpack all the definitions.
你可以通过计算来验证这一点
There are a couple nice intuitions for why it's true.
关于这一点有一些很妙的直观解释
My tentative plan is to just actually make a series about probability
我暂时的计划是做一个关于概率的系列视频
and talk about things like intuition's underlying variants and its cousins there,
来直观解释方差及其相关的概念
but right now, the main thing I want you to highlight
但现在我希望你重点关注的
is how it's the variance that adds, it's not the standard deviation that adds.
是为什么加的是方差而不是标准差
So critically,
严格来说
if you were to take 'n' different realizations of the same random variable
如果你想知道同一个随机变量出现 n 次的总和的分布长啥样
and ask what the sum looks like,
the variance of that sum is 'n' times the variance of your original variable,
那么它的方差会是原始变量方差的 n 倍
meaning the standard deviation, the square root of all this,
这意味着总和的标准差  也就是方差的平方根
is the square root of n times the original standard deviation.
是原始变量标准差的根号 n 倍
For example, back in our sequence of distributions,
例如  回到我们刚刚那张图里的分布
if we label the standard deviation of our initial one with σ,
如果我们用 σ 来表示单个随机变量分布的标准差
then the next standard deviation is going to be the square root of 2 times σ,
那么两个骰子点数和标准差将会是 根号 2 倍的 σ
and after that, it looks like the square root of 3 times σ and so on and so forth.
三个骰子的则是根号 3 倍的 σ  依此类推
This like I said is very important.
重复一遍  这一点非常重要
It means that even though our distributions are getting spread out,
因为这意味着尽管我们总和分布得越来越宽
they're not spreading out all that quickly.
但是它们并没有扩散得那么快
They only do so in proportion to the square root of the size of the sum.
这个速度正比于参与求和的变量个数的平方根
As we prepare to make a more quantitative description of the central limit theorem,
在对中心极限定理进行更加定量的描述之前
the core intuition I want you to keep in your head
我希望你能够关注的一个核心思想是
is that we'll basically realign all of these distributions
我们可以重新对齐这些分布
so that their means line up together
使它们的均值在一条线上
and then rescale them
然后缩放 x 轴
so that all of the standard deviations are just going to be equal to one.
使它们的标准差都为 1
And when we do that,
这样做所得到的分布形状
the shape that results gets closer and closer to a certain universal shape
随着变量数增多趋近于同一个形状
described with an elegant little function that will unpack in just a moment.
这个形状背后有一个优美的函数  一会就来说
And let me say one more time,
让我再叨叨一遍
the real magic here is how we could have started with any distribution
这个定理妙在于无论最初始的点数概率分布如何
describing a single roll of the die and if we play the same game,
只要保证分布不变  投更多的骰子
considering what the distributions for the many different sums look like
然后记录点数和的分布并对齐均值
and we realign them so that the means line up
再缩放 x 轴使的标准差全为 1
and we rescale them so that the standard deviations are all one,
得到的分布都很接近这个统一的形状
we still approach that same universal shape which is kind of mind-boggling.
这太颠覆认知了
And now my friends is probably as good a time
说了这么多
as any to finally get into the formula for a normal distribution.
终于可以正式聊正态分布的式子了
And the way I'd like to do this is to
我想要做的就是
basically peel back all the layers and build it up one piece at a time.
把它全部拆开再一点一点组装起来
The function eˣ or anything to the x describes exponential growth.
函数 eˣ 或者随便什么的 x 次方  表示指数增长
And if you make that exponent negative, which flips around the graph horizontally,
如果给指数前面加个负号  就会沿 y 轴函数图像
you might think of it as describing exponential decay.
可以当成是指数衰减
To make this decay in both directions,
为了让它在正负方向上都衰减
you could do something to make sure the exponent is always negative and growing,
我们要确保指数非正  而且越往两边越小
*Grant 搞错了（漏了 0）
like taking the negative absolute value,
例如取绝对值的相反数
that would give us this kind of awkward sharp point in the middle,
不过这会使中间有个奇怪的刺突
but if instead you make that exponent the negative square of x,
但如果指数是 -x²
you get a smoother version of the same thing, which decays in both directions.
不仅同样往两边衰减  还能得到更光滑的函数
This gives us the basic bell curve shape.
这样就得到了一个钟形曲线
Now, if you throw a constant in front of that x
接着  如果你在 x 前面乘一个常数
and you scale that constant up and down,
然后修改这个常数的大小
it lets you stretch and squish the graph horizontally
就可以在水平方向上伸缩图形
allowing you to describe narrow and wider bell curves.
随你的意得到窄的或者宽的曲线
And a quick thing I'd like to point out here is that
稍微插一句
based on the rules of exponentiation,
根据指数的运算法则
as we tweak around that constant c,
当我们调整常数 c 时
you could also think about it as simply changing the base of the exponentiation.
可以看作是改变了这个函数的底数
And in that sense, the number e is not really all that special for our formula.
照这样说  e 对于这个式子来说并没有什么特殊
We could replace it with any other positive constant
可以随便拿什么大于 1 的数来做底
*Grant 又搞错了（说成了正数）
you'll get the same family of curves as we tweak that constant.
当我们调整系数 c 时  得到的也是这一族曲线
Make it a two, same family of curves, make it a three, same family of curves.
底为 2 时  底为 3 时  都是这一族
The reason we use e is that it gives that constant a very readable meaning,
之所以这里用 e  是因为它给了常数 c 一个明确的意义
or rather if we reconfigure things a little bit
为了说清楚  我们先稍微改一下指数
so that the exponent looks like negative 1/2
把 x 除一个常数 σ  平方完再乘 -1/2
times x divided by a certain constant, which we'll suggestively call σ, squared,
写成 -½(x/σ)²
then once we turn this into a probability distribution,
这样一来  如果我们把它看成是函数的概率分布
that constant σ will be the standard deviation of that distribution,
常数 σ 就恰好是分布的标准差
and that's very nice.
真棒
But before we can interpret this as a probability distribution,
但要是想说它是一个概率分布
we need the area under the curve to be one.
我们还需要让曲线和概率分布的含义相匹配
And the reason for that is how the curve is interpreted.
它和 x 轴夹的面积必须为 1
Unlike discrete distributions, when it comes to something continuous,
与离散分布不同
you don't ask about the probability of a particular point.
你不会去管连续分布某一个点的概率
Instead, you ask for the probability that a value falls between two different values.
而是在意随机值落在两个值之间的概率
And what the curve is telling you is that that probability
曲线告诉你的则是
equals the area under the curve between those two values.
这个概率等于两个值中间曲线下的面积
There's a whole other video about this.
这类函数叫做概率密度函数
They're called probability density functions.
我有一期视频专门介绍它
The main point right now is the area under the entire curve
这里的关键是  曲线下的总面积
represents the probability that something happens, that some number comes up.
代表了所有可能结果的概率总和  也就是 1
That should be one, which is why we want the area under this to be one.
因此我们才希望曲线下的总面积是 1
As it stands with the basic bell curve shape of e to the negative x squared,
回到基本的钟形曲线  e 的 -x² 次方
the area is not one,  it's actually the square root of π.
它下面的面积并不是 1  而是根号 π
I know, right?
我知道你想说啥
What is π doing here?
哪来的 π？
What does this have to do with circles?
哪来的圆？
Like I said at the start, I'd love to talk all about that in the next video
前面说了  要到下一个视频才能说清楚
but if you can spare your excitement for our purposes right now,
但先冷静  回归主题
all it means is that we should divide this function by the square root of π
问题很简单  给整个函数除个根号 π
and it gives us the area we want.
不就得到想要的面积 1 了吗
Throwing back in the constants we had earlier, the 1/2 and the σ,
再把之前的 1/2 和 σ 加回来
the effect there is to stretch out the graph
这些小东西把函数图像拉宽了根号 2 倍的 σ 倍
by a factor of σ times the square root of two.
So, we also need to divide out by that in order to make sure it has an area of one,
所以还得除回去来确保总面积为 1
and combining those fractions, the factor out front looks like
把它拼回我们的式子
1 divided by σ times the square root of 2π.
系数就长成了 σ 的根号 2π 倍分之一这样
This finally is a valid probability distribution.
终于能用了
As we tweak that value σ, resulting in narrower and wider curves,
当我们改变 σ 时  曲线会变窄变宽
that constant in the front always guarantees that the area equals one.
而前面的常数确保总面积始终为 1
The special case where σ equals one has a specific name,
特殊情况是 σ 等于 1 的情况
we call it the Standard Normal Distribution
我们称之为标准正态分布
which plays an especially important role for you and me in this lesson.
它是我们这节课的主角
And all possible normal distributions
所有可能的正态分布
are not only parametrized with this value σ
参数里不仅有这个标准差 σ
but we also subtract off another constant, μ, from the variable x
还有一个 x 要减去的参数 μ
and this essentially just lets you slide the graph left and right
调整 μ 可以左右滑动图像
so that you can prescribe the mean of this distribution.
也描述了这个分布的均值
So, in short, we have two parameters:
总结一下  我们有两个参数
one describing the mean, one describing the standard deviation
μ 描述均值  σ 描述标准差
and they're all tied together in this big formula involving an e and a π.
它们都通过这个包含 e 和 π 的大公式联系在一起
Now that all of that is on the table,
现在所有这些都理清楚了
let's look back again at the idea of starting with some random variable
让我们再从随机变量开始
and asking what the distributions for sums of that variable look like.
问自己这个变量的总和的分布长什么样
As we've already gone over, when you increase the size of that sum,
就像刚刚说的一样  随着这个随机变量不断重复
the resulting distribution will shift, according to a growing mean
总和分布会不断往均值方向移动
and it slowly spreads out, according to a growing standard deviation.
并且随着标准差的逐渐增大慢慢变宽
And putting some actual formulas to it,
代入式子来说的话就是
if we know the mean of our underlying random variable, and we call it μ,
如果假设最开始随机变量的均值是 μ  标准差是 σ 的话
and we also know its standard deviation, and we call it σ,
then the mean for the sum on the bottom will be
那么下面这个总和分布的的均值
μ times the size of the sum
就会是 μ 乘以随机变量的个数
and the standard deviation will be σ times the square root of that size.
而标准差也就是 σ 乘以个数的平方根
So now, if we want to claim that this looks more and more like a bell curve,
现在我们知道钟形曲线只有均值和标准差
and a bell curve is only described by two different parameters,
如果我们想说分布逐渐趋近钟形曲线的话
the mean and the standard deviation, you know what to do.
你应该已经知道该干啥了
You could plug those two values into the formula
只要把参数代入式子
and it gives you a highly explicit, albeit kind of complicated,
就能得到一个非常精确  但是有点复杂的式子
formula for a curve that should closely fit our distribution.
而这个式子描述的曲线则应该和我们的分布相拟合
But there's another way we can describe it that's a little more elegant
此外还有一种方式
and lends itself to a very fun visual that we can build up to.
不仅描述起来更加优雅  观赏性也很强
Instead of focusing on the sum of all of these random variables,
现在我们就不要死盯着随机变量的和了
let's modify this expression a little bit
给这个式子稍微改一改
where what we'll do is we'll look at the mean that we expect that sum to take
给这个总和减掉它的均值
and we subtract it off so that our new expression has a mean of zero,
这样它均值就是零了
and then we're going to look at the standard deviation we expect of our sum
之后以同样的方式处理标准差
and divide out by that.
用刚刚得到的式子除它的标准差
Which basically just rescales the units
本质上是给它缩放了一下换了个单位
so that the standard deviation of our expression will equal one.
这样一来这个式子标准差就是 1 了
This might seem like a more complicated expression,
虽然看上去变复杂了
but it actually has a highly readable meaning.
但它的含义更明确了
It's essentially saying
它实际上是在说
'how many standard deviations away from the mean is this sum.'
这个总和离均值有多少个标准差
For example, this bar here corresponds to a certain value that you might find
例如  这个柱子表示了投十个骰子可能出现的一个点数和
when you roll 10 dice and you add them all up.
And it's position, a little above -1, is telling you that that
而它略大于 -1 的位置
value is a little bit less than one standard deviation lower than the mean.
表示这个点数和比均值小不到一个标准差
Also, by the way, in anticipation for the animation I'm trying to build to here,
提前说一句  我等下要在这里放的动画
the way I'm representing things on that lower plot is that
下面的那个图里
the area of each one of these bars is telling us
表示概率的是柱子的面积而不是高度
the probability of the corresponding value rather than the height.
You might think of the y-axis as representing not probability
也可以说成是
but a kind of probability density.
y 轴表示的不是概率而是概率密度
The reason for this is to set the stage
这样可以给后面铺垫
so that it aligns with the way we interpret continuous distributions
和连续概率分布的图像表示相统一
where the probability of falling between a range of values
也就是在随机变量取值落在一个区间内的概率
is equal to an area under a curve between those values.
等于这个区间曲线下的面积
In particular, the area of all the bars together is going to be one.
特别地  所有柱子的总面积加起来为 1
Now, with all of that in place, let's have a little fun.
讲了这么多  是时候来点好玩的了
Let me start by rolling things back so that the distribution on the bottom
让我们往前倒一点
represents a relatively small sum,
这样一来下面的分布只是少数几次加和
like adding together only three such random variables.
例如只是三个随机变量的和
Notice what happens as I change the distribution we start with.
现在如果我换一个初始概率分布
As it changes, the distribution on the bottom completely changes its shape.
注意下面的分布已经完全变了个样
It's very dependent on what we started with.
说明它的形状受初始分布影响很大
If we let the size of our sum get a little bit bigger, say going up to 10,
如果我们增加随机变量的个数  加到十个
and as I change the distribution for X,
当我改变 X 的分布时
it largely stays looking like a bell curve
它基本上还像一个钟形曲线
but I can find some distributions that get it to change shape.
但我可以找到些初始分布  使它改变形状
For example, the really lopsided one
例如极大概率出 1 和 6 的非常不平等的分布
where almost all the probability is in the numbers 1 or 6
results in this kind of spiky bell curve.
得到一个有很多峰的钟形曲线
And if you'll recall, earlier on,
如果你还记得的话
I actually showed this in the form of a simulation.
之前有一个模拟出现过这个情况
Though if you're wondering whether that spikiness
当时问到这些峰是偶然的还是真实的分布
was an artifact of the randomness or reflected the true distribution,
turns out it reflects the true distribution.
实际上它反映了真实的分布
In this case, 10 is not a large enough sum for the central limit theorem to kick in
对这个例子来说  十个随机变量不足以满足中心极限定理
but if instead I let that sum grow and I consider adding 50 different values,
但如果我让这个和增长到比如 50 个随机变量
which is actually not that big,
实际上也不是很多
then no matter how I change the distribution for underlying random variable,
但这时候无论我如何改变随机变量的概率分布
it has essentially no effect on the shape of the plot on the bottom.
它基本上对下面图里的形状没有影响
No matter where we start,
无论初始分布如何
all of the information and nuance for the distribution of X gets washed away
随机变量 X 的一切分布细节都会被抹去
and we tend towards this single universal shape
趋近于这个统一的形状
described by a very elegant function for the standard normal distribution
即背后有着优雅函数的标准正态分布
1 over square root of 2π times e to the negative x squared over 2.
*优雅的吟诵*
*吟诵的就是上面这个公式
This, this right here is what the central limit theorem is all about.
这就是中心极限定理的全部内容
Almost nothing you can do to this initial distribution
你无论对初始分布做什么
changes the shape we tend towards.
都没法改变它所趋近的形状
Now, the more theoretically minded among you
现在  如果你陶醉在理论的思想里
might still be wondering what is the actual theorem.
可能会想到底实际的定理是什么
Like, what's the mathematical statement
就是说  这里我们想证明或推翻的数学表述  是什么
that could be proved or disproved that we're claiming here.
If you want a nice formal statement, here's how it might go.
那我就来给一个形式化的表述
Consider this value
考虑把 N 个随机变量的实例相加得到的结果
where we're summing up N different instantiations of our random variable
but tweaked and tuned so that its mean and standard deviation are one.
我们把它进行微调使得均值为 0 并且标准差为 1
Again, meaning you can read it as asking
这也就等同于
how many standard deviations away from the mean is the sum.
它距离均值有多少个标准差
Then the actual rigorous no jokes this time statement of the central limit theorem
那么中心极限定理不开玩笑十分严谨的表述是这样的
is that if you consider the probability that this value
如果你考虑一个值
falls between two given real numbers, a and b,
落在两个给定的实数 a 和 b 之间的概率
and you consider the limit of that probability
从它极限的角度看
as the size of your sum goes to infinity,
当 N 趋向于无穷大时
then that limit is equal to a certain integral
这个极限的值等于某个特定的积分
which basically describes
这个积分基本上就是
the area under a standard normal distribution between those two values.
标准正态分布曲线下这两个值之间的面积
Again, there are three underlying assumptions that I have yet to tell you,
再重复一次  有三个基本假设我还没有告诉你们
but other than those, in all of its gory detail,
除了这些
this right here is the central limit theorem.
就基本上是中心极限定理的所有细节了
All of that is a bit theoretical,
这些说起来都挺理论的
so it might be helpful to bring things back down to earth
可能说人话更方便理解
and turn back to the concrete example that I mentioned at the start
回到最开始提到的现实中的例子
where you imagine rolling a die 100 times,
假如掷一个骰子一百次
and let's assume it's a fair die for this example,
然后把点数和加在一起
and you add together the results.
假设它是公平的骰子
The challenge for you is to find a range of values
你现在要找到一个越小越好的范围
such that you're 95% sure that the sum will fall within this range.
使得你有 95% 的把握保证点数和会落在这个范围内
For questions like this,
对于这类问题
there's a handy rule of thumb about normal distributions
正态分布有一个方便的经验法则
which is that about 68% of your values
即约 68% 的值
are going to fall within one standard deviation of the mean.
会落在离均值一个标准差之内
95% of your values, the thing we care about,
95% 的值  刚好我们这里要用到
fall within two standard deviations of the mean
落在离均值两个标准差之内
and a whopping 99.7% of your values
而高达 99.7% 的值
will fall within three standard deviations of the mean.
会落在离均值三个标准差之内
It's a rule of thumb that's commonly memorized
这是经常接触统计概率的人
by people who do a lot of probability and stats.
耳熟能详的经验法则
Naturally, this gives us what we need for our example
而这自然也就给了我们的例子所需的东西
and let me go ahead and draw out what this would look like
现在让我现在把它实际画出来
where I'll show the distribution for a fair die up at the top
上面的图展示的是公平骰子的概率分布
and the distribution for a sum of 100 such dice on the bottom.
底部展示 100 个这样的骰子点数和的分布
Which by now as you know looks like a certain normal distribution.
现在你知道  这看起来像某个正态分布
Step one with a problem like this
为了找到这个确切的分布
is to find the mean of your initial distribution.
第一步是找到初始分布的均值
Which in this case will look like 1/6 times 1 plus 1/6 times 2, on and on and on
这个例子里就是 1/6 * 1 + 1/6 * 2 + ...
and works out to be 3.5.
结果是 3.5
We also need the standard deviation which requires calculating the variance,
我们还需要找到标准差  也就是首先需要计算方差
which as you know
正如你所知
involves adding all the squares of the differences between the values and the means
方差是(各个值与均值之差)的平方和
and it works out to be 2.92.
这里结果是 2.92
Square root of that comes out to be 1.71.
开平方后得到 1.71
Those are the only two numbers we need
这就是我们所需要的全部两个数字
and I will invite you again to reflect
并且我再次请你思考一下
on how magical it is that those are the only two numbers that you need
这是有多神奇  也就是说只需要这两个数
to completely understand the bottom distribution.
你就能完全理解确定下面图中的分布
Its mean will be 100 times μ, which is 350
它的均值将是 100μ  即 350
and its standard deviation will be the square root of 100 times σ.
它的标准差将是(根号 100)倍的 σ
So, 10 times σ, 17.1.
也就是 10σ  即 17.1
Remembering our handy rule of thumb,
回忆一下我们之前的 3σ 原则
we're looking for values two standard deviations away from the mean
我们的目的就是寻找 距离均值两个标准差的值
and when you subtract two σ from the mean, you end up with about 316,
这里均值减去 2σ 大概是 316
and when you add two σ, you end up with roughly 384.
均值加上 2σ 大概是 384
And there you go... That gives us the answer.
就是这样  答案就是这么简单
Okay, I promise to wrap things up shortly,
好吧  我保证不拖堂太久  就总结一下
but while we're on this example,
但在这个例子中
there's one - more question that's worth your time to ponder.
还有一个问题值得你花时间思考
Instead of just asking about the sum of 100 die rolls,
现在我不问投 100 次骰子的点数和了
let's say I had you divide that number by 100,
而是让你将这个数字除以 100
which basically means all the numbers in our diagram in the bottom get divided by 100.
这也就意味着画面下半部分中的所有数字都要除以 100
Take a moment to interpret what this all would be saying then.
花点时间考虑一下这意味着什么
The expression essentially tells you
这个表达式其实是在计算
the empirical average for 100 different die rolls
掷 100 次骰子实际的平均点数
and that interval we found is now telling you
并且我们找的那个区间其实是
what range you are expecting to see for that empirical average.
你预期觉得平均点数会落在的范围
In other words, you might expect it to be around 3.5 -
换句话说  你可能期望它在 3.5 左右
that's the expected value for a die roll,
这是一个骰子掷出的期望值
but what's much less obvious and what the central limit theorem lets you compute
但不那么明显的是  中心极限定理告诉你的是
is how close to that expected value you'll reasonably find yourself.
合理范围内  你投的点数和期望值之间会差多少
In particular, it's worth your time to take a moment mulling over what
这时就尤其值得你花点时间去弄清楚
the standard deviation for this empirical average is
这个实际平均点数的标准差有多大
and what happens to it as you look at a bigger and bigger sample of die rolls.
以及当你掷越来越多的骰子时 标准差会怎么变
Lastly, but probably most importantly,
最后  但可能最重要的是
let's talk about the assumptions that go into this theorem.
让我们谈谈这个定理的假设
The first one is that all of these variables that we're adding up
第一个是我们相加的所有这些变量
are independent from each other.
是相互独立的
The outcome of one process doesn't influence the outcome of any other process.
也就是一个过程的结果不会影响其他任何过程的结果
The second is that all of these variables are drawn from the same distribution.
第二个是所有这些变量都遵循相同的分布
Both of these have been implicitly assumed with our dice example.
在我们前面掷骰子的例子中  这两个假设都是隐含的
We've been treating the outcome of each die roll
我们一直将每次掷骰子的结果
as independent from the outcome of all the others
视为独立于剩下每次掷骰子的结果
and we're assuming that each die follows the same distribution.
并假设每个骰子遵循相同的分布
Sometimes in the literature you'll see
有时在文献中
these two assumptions lumped together under the initials i.i.d
你会看到这两个假设合在一起  用首字母缩写 i.i.d
for Independent and identically distributed.
表示 独立同分布
One situation where these assumptions are decidedly NOT true
一个这些假设明显不成立的情况
would be the Galton board.
正是高尔顿板
I mean, think about it
我意思是  你想想看
is it the case that the way a ball bounces off of one of the pegs
一个球在一个钉子上弹开的方式
is independent from how it's going to bounce off the next peg?
是否独立于它在下一个钉子上弹开的方式
Absolutely not.
绝对不是
Depending on the last bounce,
取决于前一次的弹跳
it's coming in with a completely different trajectory.
之后它的轨迹也会完全不同
And is it the case that the distribution of possible outcomes off of each peg
并且  小球在每一个钉子上的弹向分布
are the same for each peg that it hits?
是否跟之前钉子的都一样？
Again, almost certainly not.
同样  几乎肯定不是
Maybe it hits one peg glancing to the left,
也许它在一个钉子上向左斜着击中
meaning the outcomes are hugely skewed in that direction
这意味着弹跳的方向向左严重偏斜
and then hits the next one glancing to the right.
然后在下一个钉子上向右斜着击中
When I made all those simplifying assumptions in the opening example,
在开篇的示例中  我做了所有假设来简化
it wasn't just to make this easier to think about.
并不仅仅是为了让它更容易思考
It's also that those assumptions were necessary
这些假设也是必要的
for this to actually be an example of the central limit theorem.
因为这实际上是中心极限定理的一个要求
Nevertheless, it seems to be true that for the real Galton board,
尽管如此  在真实的高尔顿板上
despite violating both of these,
即使违反了这两个假设
a normal distribution does kind of come about...
正态分布似乎还是会出现……
Part of the reason might be that there are generalizations of the theorem
部分原因是中心极限定理有更通用的形式
beyond the scope of this video that relax these assumptions,
可以放宽这些假设
especially the second one.
尤其是第二个假设
But I do want to caution you against the fact that many times,
但我确实想提醒你  很多时候
people seem to assume that a variable is normally distributed
即使没有验证是否满足这些假设
even when there's no actual justification to do so.
人们似乎也会默认这个变量服从正态分布
The third assumption is actually fairly subtle.
第三个假设实际上相当微妙
It's that the variance we've been computing for these variables is finite.
也就是  这些变量的方差要求是有限的
This was never an issue for the dice example
对于掷骰子的例子来说  这肯定不是问题
because there were only six possible outcomes,
因为只有六个可能的结果
but in certain situations where you have an infinite set of outcomes,
但比如当结果的范围是无限的时候
when you go to compute the variance,
你再去计算方差
the sum ends up diverging off to infinity.
总和有可能会发散至无穷
These can be perfectly valid probability distributions
这类概率分布完全可能存在
and they do come up in practice
在应用中也确实会出现
but in those situations
但是在这些情况下
as you consider, adding many different instantiations of that variable
当你把许多这样的随机变量相加
and letting that sum approach infinity,
并且总和趋近于无穷大时
even if the first two assumptions hold,
即使前两个假设成立
it is very much a possibility that the thing you tender towards
很有可能你最终得到的东西
is not actually a normal distribution.
实际上并不是正态分布
If you've understood everything up to this point,
如果你理解了到目前为止的所有内容
you now have a very strong foundation
那么你现在对中心极限定理的本质
in what the central limit theorem is all about.
已经有了非常扎实的基础
And next up, I'd like to explain
接下来的视频中  我想解释
why it is that this particular function is the thing that we tend towards
为什么这个特定的函数是我们想要的东西
and why it has a π in it -
以及这个公式里面为什么有一个 π
what it has to do with circles.
这个式子和圆又有什么关系